Guide to the Oregon State University Military Photographs Collection 1875-1975
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center
- World War One, 1916-1918; Series II
  - Glass Lantern Slide Collection, Military training aids, circa 1919
    - Tank filling station with concrete horse trough, circa 1918; P002:142; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Slide caption: "Tank filling station with concrete horse trough, Boucq." Location in France, probably Northern area near front lines, town of Boucq. Marked: "Water Supply no.39"
    - Mobile purification truck, water supply, circa 1918; P002:143; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Caption of slide: "Side view of Mobile purification truck - "Sterilab". Showing pumping and filtering equipment in rear with laboratory space in front." Unique piece of US Army Engineer Corps equipment. Shown on city street, unknown location. Marked: "Water supply No.38"
    - 60" Aluminum Construction High Power Search Light, circa 1918; P002:144; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      slide group showing different types of searchlights, mounted on trucks and wagon carts. Although not new technology to WWI, the use of searchlights to spot incoming enemy aircraft was a new tactic. German heavy bombers and airships were able to penetrate deep into France (Target Paris) and over the channel to England (Target London) and the use of large searchlights became commonplace. This group of slides shows the large lights used in WWI. Slide Marked: "Searchlights n66"
    - 60" Sperry Light Weight Barrel Searchlight and carriage, circa 1918; P002:145; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Slide group showing different types of searchlights, mounted on trucks and wagon carts. Although not new technology to WWI, the use of searchlights to spot incoming enemy aircraft was a new tactic. German heavy bombers and airships were able to penetrate deep into France (Target Paris) and over the channel to England (Target London) and the use of large searchlights became commonplace. This group of slides shows the large lights used in WWI. Slide Marked: "Searchlights n59"
    - 60" Aluminum Construction High Power Searchlight on truck, circa 1918; P002:146; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Slide group showing different types of searchlights, mounted on trucks and wagon carts. Although not new technology to WWI, the use of searchlights to spot incoming enemy aircraft was a new tactic. German heavy bombers and airships were able to penetrate deep into France (Target Paris) and over the channel to England (Target London) and the use of large searchlights became commonplace. This group of slides shows the large lights used in WWI. Slide Marked: "Searchlights n61"
    - High Intensity Search Light, Sperry light, GE Drum, circa 1918; P002:147; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Slide group showing different types of searchlights, mounted on trucks and wagon carts. Although not new technology to WWI, the use of searchlights to spot incoming enemy aircraft was a new tactic. German heavy bombers and airships were able to penetrate deep into France (Target Paris) and over the channel to England (Target London) and the use of large searchlights became commonplace. This group of slides shows the large lights used in WWI. Slide Marked: "Searchlights n62"
    - Sperry light weight Searchlight, circa 1918; P002:148; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Slide group showing different types of searchlights, mounted on trucks and wagon carts. Although not new technology to WWI, the use of searchlights to spot incoming enemy aircraft was a new tactic. German heavy bombers and airships were able to penetrate deep into France (Target Paris) and over the channel to England (Target London) and the use of large searchlights became commonplace. This group of slides shows the large lights used in WWI. Slide Marked: "Searchlights n64"
    - 60" Sperry High Intensity Light, Open type 1st model, circa 1918; P002:149; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Slide group showing different types of searchlights, mounted on trucks and wagon carts. Although not new technology to WWI, the use of searchlights to spot incoming enemy aircraft was a new tactic. German heavy bombers and airships were able to penetrate deep into France (Target Paris) and over the channel to England (Target London) and the use of large searchlights became a necessity. This group of slides shows the large lights used in WWI. Slide Marked: "Searchlights n60"
    - Sperry High Intensity Open Type, Army Design, circa 1918; P002:150; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Slide group showing different types of searchlights, mounted on trucks and wagon carts. Although not new technology to WWI, the use of searchlights to spot incoming enemy aircraft was a new tactic. German heavy bombers and airships were able to penetrate deep into France (Target Paris) and over the channel to England (Target London) and the use of large searchlights became commonplace. This group of slides shows the large lights used in WWI. Slide Marked: "Searchlights n68"
    - Diagram of Machine Gun Emplacement, circa 1918; P002:151; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Diagram of standard machine gun emplacement in trenches. Shown with sizes of openings and walkways. Marked: "F.F.37"
    - Soldiers training in trench, unknown location, circa 1918; P002:152; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Men in trench training with unknown weapons. Uniforms are standard issue with campaign hats. Tents in background suggest a stateside training base. Marked: "F.F. 32"
    - Trench with sandbag fortification, training base, circa 1918; P002:153; glass lantern slide (Box 3)
      Sandbag reinforced trench design, possibly at training base stateside. Barracks and tents in background suggest a stateside training base. Marked "F.F. 40"
    - Temporary bridge, France, circa 1918; P002:154; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Temporary foot bridge constructed by US Army Engineers, somewhere in France, late 1918. Photograph shows 2 sections of bridge needing repair, possibly from battle damage. The slide is marked with the "Bridge Construction no. 33" but in faint pencil on the label is written "Boche 4hrs". This notation has no explanation, but possibly could be that the Germans ("boche") had damaged the bridge and it was repaired in 4 hours.
    - Diagram of 60 foot Portable Road Bridge, circa 1918; P002:155; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Line drawing of the "Portable Road Bridge 60'0" Span Class A Erection Diagram". Slide shows the complete specifications for the bridge with instructions about winches and timber derricks for building. How block and tackle was to be set up with specifications on size of wire rope and dimensions of pilings is given. Marked: "Bridge Construction No. 38".
    - Mules with supply wagons crossing bridge, circa 1918; P002:156; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Mule drawn wagon with supplies crossing a temporary wood bridge, somewhere in France, 1918. The supply column (also known as "train") can be seen on far bank of river. US Soldier leading the mule team is wearing British style steel helmet. Of note is the rifle scabbard attached to the saddle on the mule team. Marked: "Bridge Construction No. 35"
    - Repaired bridge, bombed out section replaced, circa 1918; P002:157; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Section of old stone arch bridge being repaired by US Army Engineers. Bombed out section has been rebuilt with timber construction. Soldiers are seen on top of repaired section. Probably France, late 1918. Marked: "Bridge Construction No.40".
    - Soldiers rebuilding bridge in bomb ravaged town, circa 1918; P002:158; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      US Army Engineers repairing a destroyed bridge with new heavy timber construction. Heavily bombed out buildings in background, showing the devastation of French towns on the front lines. Soldiers are wearing British design steel helmets and web gear. Probably somewhere in France, late 1918. Marked: "Bridge Construction No. 46".
    - 303rd Engineers foot bridge, France, circa 1918; P002:159; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Simple construction of foot bridge, temporary structure. Slide caption: "1-4 Foot bridge #13 291.5-86-2 Buzancy Sheet 10-29-18 Aire River 303 Eng". Bridge constructed by the 303rd Engineering battalion, the nomenclature is possibly a standardized design number for temporary foot bridges. Marked: "F.B. No.47".
    - 303rd Engineers foot bridge, France #2, circa 1918; P002:160; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Simple construction of foot bridge, temporary structure. Slide caption: "17 - 303rd Engrs Foot Bridge #5 294.9-85.3 Buzancy Sheet Aire R. 11-6-18". Bridge constructed by the 303rd Engineering battalion, the nomenclature is possibly a standardized design number for temporary foot bridges. Marked: "F.B. No.44"
    - 303rd Engineers foot bridge, France #3, circa 1918; P002:161; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Temporary foot bridge built by US Army Engineers, France, 1918. Caption of slide: "1-8 Foot Bridge #17 291.25-85.9 Buzancy Sheet, 10-29-18 Aire R. 303 Eng." Marked: "F.B. No. 49".
    - 303rd Engineers foot bridge, France #4, circa 1918; P002:162; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Temporary foot bridge built by US Army Engineers, France 1918. Caption of slide: "1-9 Foot Bridge #23 289-8 285.5 Vouziers Sheet 10-29-18 Aire R. 303 Eng." Marked F.B. No.46".
    - 303rd Engineers foot bridge, France #5, circa 1918; P002:163; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Temporary foot bridge built by US Army Engineers, France 1918. Caption of slide: "1-7 Foot Bridge #16 291.2-85.05 Buzancy Sheet 10-29-18 Aire R. 303 Eng." Marked F.B. No.48".
    - Duplicate Slide of Supply Wagons on Bridge, circa 1918; P002:164; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Duplicate slide of P002:091 Supply wagons on road with US Soldiers. Probably in France, horse-drawn supply wagons with covered loads are preparing to cross a stone bridge. Soldiers are wearing heavy overcoats and garrison caps.
    - Duplicate slide of Motor cycles in village, circa 1918; P002:165; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Duplicate of slide P002:096. US Army personnel on motorcycles driving through small French town. Motorcycles are probably Indian or Harley Davidson manufacture. With the strategic value of motorcycles proven to the military,the War Department relied heavily upon Harley-Davidson following the entry of the United States into World War I. At war’s end, some 20,000 Harley-Davidson and Indian motorcycles had been used by the military.
    - US Soldiers inspecting French locomotive, circa 1918; P002:166; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      US Army railroad personnel inspecting a French steam locomotive. Soldiers are working on the running gear of this large 2-8-0 style steam engine. Officers appear to be looking on at right. In the engine's cab are two men, probably French engineer and fireman wearing civilian company uniforms with brimmed caps. The markings of the French Railroad have been painted over and "USA" is stenciled below. Steam engine appears to be a standard freight hauling engine of the era. Marked: "R.R. Sta. Gauge No.16" This denotes the standard gauge railroad equipment (4 feet, 8 1/2" wide) as opposed to the smaller 2 foot gauge used.
    - Soldiers playing baseball, circa 1918; P002:167; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      US Soldiers playing the American pass-time, somewhere in France. Men playing baseball are wearing their uniforms with campaign hats and leggings. Catcher has face mask and chest protector equipment..
    - FWD type truck loaded on flatcar, France 1918, circa 1918; P002:168; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      US Army standard FWD truck loaded onto a French Railroad flatcar, with soldiers looking on. The truck is he F.W.D. Model B, built by the Four Wheel Drive Co. of Clintonville, Wisconsin, this was a four-wheel drive vehicle. Rated as a 3-tonner, the F. W.D. had a Wisconsin four-cylinder petrol engine with a three-speed gearbox and a two¬speed transfer gearbox. There was a shaft drive to each axle. On roads the F.W.D. was driven as a normal rear-wheel drive vehicle, but for off road driving an additional gear lever was provided on the chassis side which controlled the low gears and connected up the drive to the front axle. Slide is marked: R.S.G. no.14" The RSG indicates Railroad Standard Gauge..
    - Soldiers clearing ground for railroad roadbed, circa 1918; P002:170; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Soldiers digging a right of way for railroad in forest, somewhere in France. Based on the label of the slide, "R.R. Sta. Gauge No.13", this excavation must be for a roadbed for trackage. Soldiers are wearing a variety of uniform pieces, including garrison caps and steel helmets. Some men have the gas mask canvas bag worn on their chests.
    - Soldiers erecting camouflage netting, circa 1918; P002:171; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Soldiers erecting camouflage netting on short poles in field. The structure is temporary, poles appear to be tree branches. There is nothing under the netting, probably to camouflage supplies later. Soldiers are wearing field gear with helmets. One soldier is standing guard with rifle. Marked: "D.C. & M. 36".
    - Exploded shell casings in pile, circa 1918; P002:172; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Photo of twisted metal in field, possibly exploded shell casings. Unknown location or purpose of photograph. Metal appears to be torn and twisted, but they are the casings of the shells and not the projectile. Marked: "D.C. & M.36".
    - Returning allied prisoners on road, Nov 25, 1918, circa 1918; P002:173; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      The category of the slide is camouflage, which is evident by the netting over the road. The caption is more descriptive of the importance of the image, "Verdun Etain road, returning allied prisoners, November 25,1918" Almost two weeks after the Armistice, the repatriation of prisoners on both sides was a slow process. Soldiers are marching in formation on the open road, no vehicles in sight. The road is lined on both sides by camouflaged fencing and large camouflage nets are strung at intervals in the trees lining the lane. marked" Camouflage No.28".
    - Soldiers working in sawmill, France, circa 1918; P002:174; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Sawmill operations in France, manned by US Soldiers. Overall view of sawmill building and log piles. Of note is a small, narrow gauge locomotive pulling two cars with logs. The engine is not a steam locomotive, and is probably a very early type powered by a gasoline engine. Four tall smokestacks at rear of facility, probably for boilers to operate the steam powered machinery in sawmill. Marked: "Forestry No.2".
    - Sawmill operations with US Soldiers, France, circa 1918; P002:175; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      US Soldiers moving a large tree with a wheeled carrier and horses. Logging operations with US Soldiers in France. US Army personnel are working with civilians to move a large log. In background are standard gauge railroad cars, waiting to be loaded. Glass lantern slide is damaged on right with black scorching from heat. Marked: "Forestry No. 3".
    - Army Engineers building road, France, circa 1918; P002:176; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      US Army Engineers working on roadbed, somewhere in France during WWI. Men working with hand tools to repair ruts in dirt road. Four men working with a collection of others looking on. Truck on road in background is the FWD type cargo truck. Marked: "Highway Const. 62 Set 1".
    - Soldiers repairing road mine crater, Nov 12, 1918, circa; P002:177; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      US Army Engineers repairing damage to road made by a mine. Very large crater is being hand filled and leveled by soldiers. The caption on slide reads: "Repairing road mine crater, 12 November 1918" Of special note is the date, one day after signing of the armistice, peace had been declared, no celebration for these dough boys, just more back breaking work as Army Engineers. Marked: "Highway const No. 58".
    - Road repair by US Army Engineers, 12 Nov 1918, circa 1918; P002:178; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      US Army 101st Engineers repairing road in France, 12 November 1918. One day after the end of WWI, no celebration for these dough boys, more work for them repairing war damaged roads. Crates of materials on side of road. Marked: "Highway construction No57".
    - Road Construction diagram, circa 1918; P002:179; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Diagram of two types of road construction used by US Army Engineers. Single-way Macadam Road, showing drainage ditches and depth of grading materials. Figure 2 shows plans for widening an existing roadway. Plans show adding 4" to 9" of wearing surface to tops of roadways. Marked: "Highway Construction No.53".
    - Diagram of planked roadway construction, circa 1918; P002:185; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      US Army Engineers training diagram of roadway construction using wood planks. Fig.4 shows an 18 foot wide roadbed cross section. Fig. 5 is a cross section of a shell hole. This is to instruct Engineers on methods used to repair bomb craters in roadways. Fig. 6 is the completed repair showing a base of sandbags and material added to fill in crater. Marked: "Highway Construction no. 54".
    - Highway near Malancourt, France, circa 1918; P002:187; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Photo showing the Highway (actually dirt road with ruts) from Malancourt, France. Road leads off into the distance where a pair of military trucks can be seen. Marked: "Highway construction No.60".
    - Soldiers pulling down ruined wall, France, circa 1918; P002:188; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      Crew of US Army Engineers pulling down a brick wall in a bombed out building. Ropes are attached to the crumbling wall and 2 groups of approximately 20 men each are pulling down the wall. Men are all wearing their steel helmets, which appears to be an excellent idea at the time. Marked "Highway construction 61 set 1".
    - US soldiers walking through ruins of French town, circa 1918; P002:189; glass lantern slide (Box 4)
      US Soldiers walking through a bombed out French village. The main topic of the slide appears to be the road in the town, which is little more than a muddy trail. Destruction of the buildings in the background shows the effect of total war on civilians in Europe during WWI. Marked: "Highway constn 63, set 1".
  - OAC Cadets leaving for WWI, August 1918
    Photos in sub series show scenes of OAC Company K formations leaving on trains for WWI. photographs can be dated between Summer 1917 and Fall 1918 based on entries in the 1919 Oregon Beaver Yearbook which has a section specially dedicated to OAC Cadets serving "Over There". The company is marching to the railroad station on sixth street, most likely a Southern Pacific dedicated troop train. Series of photographs include crowds saying goodbye to the OAC cadets as they leave for training.
    - Citizens sending off OAC Company K departing train in distance, circa 1918; P002:190; 4x5 photographic print (Box 1)
      Second photograph of citizens sending off OAC Company K to duty in WWI with train in distance. Related to P002:193, photo shows crowd breaking up as train leaves in the background. The destination for the cadets is unclear, probably training bases stateside before being transferred to France. Dating of photograph is between Summer 1917 and Fall 1918 based on entries in the 1919 Oregon Beaver Yearbook which has a section specially dedicated to OAC Cadets serving "Over There". Stamped on reverse top right with Oregon Agricultural College Library.
    - OAC Company K Formation marching to train station 1918, circa 1918; P002:191; 4x5 photographic print (Box 1)
      Formation of OSC Cadets marching on Corvallis Street. Previous description states Company K leaving for WWI. P002:191 and 192 show cadets marching with blanket rolls over their shoulders and the standard issue campaign hats. Men are being escorted by citizens, with many onlookers curbside. The destination for the cadets is unclear, probably training bases stateside before being transferred to France. Dating of photograph is between Summer 1917 and Fall 1918 based on entries in the 1919 Oregon Beaver Yearbook which has a section specially dedicated to OAC Cadets serving "Over There". Stamped on reverse top right with Oregon Agricultural College Library.
    - Enlargement of Troops Company K leaving for WWI, circa 1918; P002:192; 4x5 photographic print (Box 1)
      Enlargement of formation of OAC cadets leaving for WWI. Formation of OSC Cadets marching on Corvallis Street. Previous description states Company K leaving for WWI. P002:191 and 192 show cadets marching with blanket rolls over their shoulders and the standard issue campaign hats. Men are being escorted by citizens, with many onlookers curbside. The destination for the cadets is unclear, probably training bases stateside before being transferred to France. Dating of photograph is between Summer 1917 and Fall 1918 based on entries in the 1919 Oregon Beaver Yearbook which has a section specially dedicated to OAC Cadets serving "Over There". Stamped on reverse top right with Oregon Agricultural College Library.
    - Citizens sending off OAC Company K for duty in WWI, circa 1918; P002:193; 4x5 photographic print (Box 1)
      Group of citizens attending send off for the OAC Company K cadets for duty in WWI. Photo shows train about to depart from station. The destination for the cadets is unclear, probably training bases stateside before being transferred to France. Dating of photograph is between Summer 1917 and Fall 1918 based on entries in the 1919 Oregon Beaver Yearbook which has a section specially dedicated to OAC Cadets serving "Over There". Stamped on reverse top right with Oregon Agricultural College Library.
    - OAC Cadet Band playing for departing troops 1918, circa 1918; P002:576; 4x5 photographic print (Box 1)
      Cadet band playing for departing OAC trainees. Probably the departure of Company K as referenced in others in sub series. Citizens looking on, OAC Cadet band playing in foreground. Railroad passenger cars are of the WWI era heavy steel construction style.
    - Corvallis citizens saying goodbye to OAC Cadets 1918, circa 1918; P002:577; 4x5 photographic print (Box 1)
      Corvallis citizens saying goodbye to OAC Cadet Company on train. Cadets can be seen hanging out of windows. Probably the departure of Company K as referenced in others in sub series. Citizens looking on, OAC Cadet band playing in foreground. Railroad passenger cars are of the WWI era heavy steel construction style.
    - Corvallis citizens at train with boarding cadets 1918, circa 1918; P002:578; 4x5 photographic print (Box 1)
      Corvallis citizens saying goodbye to departing Cadet troops. Cadets are wearing campaign hats with over the shoulder bedrolls. Probably the departure of Company K as referenced in others in sub series. Citizens looking on, line of troops walking next to railroad passenger cars. Railroad passenger cars are of the WWI era heavy steel construction style.
  - General Ulysses Grant Mc Alexander, Rock of the Marne, circa 1920